[Yoruba: Freeborn Ijebu-Ode son,]
[يوربي: مولود بحرية ابن أيجيبو أودي سان]
[of true Ogbogbo Clan,]
[من عشيرة أوغبوغبو،]
[whose wealth and resources surpass all that Europe ever had,]
[والتي تجاوزت ثرواتها ومواردها، كل ماكان في أوروبا]
[whose altar is filled with gold.]
[والذي ملأ مذبحة بالذهب]
This chant is called the oríkì.
تدعى هذه السلسلة بــ(أوكارو)
My grandmother used to sing it to me when I was a child in Nigeria.
اعتادت جدتي أن تغنيها لي عندما كنتُ في نيجيريا.
See, an oríkì is the song of praise of the Yoruba people,
انظر، الأوكاري هي أغنية مجد الشعب اليروبي.
and this particularly speaks of treasures that the West does not have.
وتتحدث هذه الأغنية عن الكنوز التي لا يملكها المجتمع الغربي.
Mama -- that's what I call my grandmother --
ماما-- هذا ما أنادي به جدتي--
told me many stories about Yoruba mythology.
أخبروني عن قصص عديدة عن الميثالوجيا اليوربي
You see, the Yorubas are an ethnic group from the southwestern part of Nigeria,
كما ترون، اليوروباس هم مجموعة عرقية من الجزء الجنوبي الغربي من نيجيريا،
and I was always fascinated by these stories.
ولطالما كنتُ مذهولاً بتلك القصص،
I was always intrigued.
ولطالما كنتُ مفتوناً بها.
And Yoruba culture has inspired my art since I was a child.
كما أن الثقافة اليوروباسية ألهمت فني منذ كنتُ طفلاً.
You see, African art is not just what you buy at Harlem markets in New York.
كما ترون، الفن الإفريقي ليس ماتشريه من محلات هارلم في نيويورك.
Every artist has a name,
فلكل فنان أسم،
and every artist has a story.
ولكل فنان قصة.
This is my story.
وهذه قصتي.
See, mama had tattoos on her arms and her legs.
كم ترون، كان لأمي وشوم على يديها ورجليها،
As a child, I thought she was born with them,
وعندما كنتُ طفلاً اعتقدت أنها وُلدت بهم،
with beautiful black lines and detailed symbols.
مع خطوط سوداء جميلة ورموز مفصلة،
And then she told me
ثم أخبرتني
that they were actually symbols from the Yoruba mythology.
بأن هذه الرموز بالحقيقة تعود للأساطير اليوربية.
I never knew how this was going to influence the artist that I am today.
ولم اكن أدري كيف ألهم ذلك الفنان الذي أصبحته.
You see, as a young child, I saw art everywhere.
كما ترون، كطفل صغير رأيت الفن في كل مكان.
I remember the house we lived in in Ilorin, in Stadium Road.
أتذكر المنزل الذي عشت فيه في أيلورين في شارع الستاديوم.
We had marble floors,
كان لدينا أرضية رخامية،
and you know, I would look at the marble floors,
وتدورن، كنت انظر الى الأرض الرخامية،
and I would see all sorts of patterns and designs in it,
وكنت أرى الكثير من أنواع الأنماط والتصاميم بها،
and I thought everybody could see them.
واعتقدت حينها أن باستطاعة الجميع رؤيتهم.
So I would call my brother, and I would be like,
لذلك كنتُ أنادي اخي وكنت أقول:
"Ikeolu, come and see this marble design, see this pattern, see this mask."
"أيكولو، تعال انظر لهذه التصاميم الرخامية أنظر لهذا النمط، وهذا القناع."
And he would tell me, "Laolu, I don't see anything."
وكان يخبرني، "لايلو، لا أستيطع رؤية اي شيء"
So I would use ink, and I would trace out what I saw on the floor.
وكنت أستخدم الحبر حتى أتعقب ما أراه على الأرضية.
And then when my mom noticed, she got really upset.
ولكن عندما لاحظت أمي ذلك غضبت بشدة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But that didn't stop me.
لكن ذلك لم يوقفني
I switched from ink to chalk,
واستبدلت الحبر بالطبشور،
because I got in trouble a lot with my teachers and my parents.
لأنني تسببت بمشاكل كثيرة مع أساتذتي وأهلي.
So I remember my mom said, "Laolu, we are Christians.
لذلك تذكرت قول أمي، "لايلو، نحن مسيحيين
Why don't you draw like other people?
لم لا ترسم مثل بقية الناس؟
Why don't you draw landscapes or maybe you draw chairs or furniture,
لم لا ترسم بعض المناظر الطبيعية أو ربما كرسي أو نافورة،
or maybe even draw Jesus?"
أو ربما يسوع المسيح ؟"
You know, I could paint the whole house if I had a chance,
أتدرون، كان بإمكاني الرسم على كل المنزل إذا أوتيت الفرصة،
but when I grew up, I knew being an artist was not an option,
لكن عندما كبرت أدركت أن كوني فناناً ليس خياراً
so I wanted to be the person my parents wanted me to be,
لذلك أردت أن اكون الإنسان الذي أراده أهلي أن أكون،
so I went to law school.
لذلك ذهبت الى كلية الحقوق.
Of course, that's my dad there. He was so proud that day.
بالطبع، هذا أبي هناك كان فخوراً جداً ذلك اليوم.
And this was what my notebooks looked like in law school.
وهذا مابدى عليه دفتر ملاحظاتي في كلية الحقوق
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Of course I would miss classes,
بالطبع، كنتُ أفوت الحصص،
and I would make up excuses why I wasn't going to class.
وكنتُ ألفق الأعذار لعدم حضوري للصف.
But when I started working at the Human Rights Commission
لكن عندما بدأت العمل في لجنة حقوق الإنسان
as a human rights attorney,
كمحامي حقوق الإنسان،
my mind was elsewhere.
كان عقلي في مكان أخر.
I saw a very tough reality.
رأيت واقع أليم جداً.
I worked with children
عملت مع الأطفال
who had to choose between getting an education
اللذين كان عليهم الاختيار بين حصولهم على تعليم
and actually being forced into marriage.
أو إرغامهم على الزواج.
I was so frustrated seeing all the injustice around me,
وكنتُ غاضباً من رؤية كل ذلك الظلم حولي،
and my only outlet was art,
وكان منفذي الوحيد هو الفن،
so I started painting.
لذلك بدأت بالرسم.
This piece is called "Dreamscape."
اسم هذه اللوحة "دريمسكيب" (مهرب الأحلام)
So when you zoom into this piece,
وعندما تكبر هذه الوحة
you're going to see a girl child
سترى طفلة صغيرة
and the accidental birth,
والولادة الغير مقصودة،
the fact that our future is controlled by where we are born.
وحقيقة أن مستقبلنا يحدده مكان ولادتنا.
Now, the next one you see a man and a man holding hands,
والآن، ما ستراه تالياً هو رجلان يمسكان بأيدي بعضهما،
a woman and a woman holding hands.
وأمرأتان تمسكان بأيدي بعضهما،
You see, in Nigeria, same-sex relationship is criminalized.
كما ترون، في نيجريا العلاقات أحادية الجنس يحاسب عليها القانون
You can actually get 14 years for that.
ومن الممكن أن تحاكم بــ 14 سنة لذلك.
With my art, I like to tell stories.
وبفني، أرغب بأن أروي قصص،
Through my art, I like to start a conversation.
وخلال فني، أرغب ببدء نقاش.
So in this one, you see the map of Africa,
اذاً، بهذه اللوحة سترون خريطة أفريقيا،
you see the questions, you see crying,
وكما ترون الأسئلة، ترون البكاء،
and there you see syringes plugged into Africa
وهنا ترون الحقنات تصل الى أفريقيا
and the natural resources being drained out.
ويتم استنزاف المصادر الطبيعية.
So I asked myself, where does it go?
لذلك سألت نفسي، لأين تذهب؟
Who benefits from all of this?
من يستفيد من كل ذلك ؟
You see, with my art,
وكما تورن، مع فني،
the way I weave my art around the patterns, the masks, the stories,
والطريقة التي ينسج بها فني الأنماط، الأقنعة، والقصص،
and the way I use my lines,
والطريقة التي استخدم بها خطوطي،
it's all from the Yoruba culture.
كلها من ثقافة اليوربا
So in 2013, I made a big gamble.
لذلك في عام 2013، قمت بمجازفة كبيرة.
I quit my job and I moved to New York City to practice art full time.
استقلت من ملي وانتقلت لمدينة نيويورك لأعمل بداوم كامل
Of course, my parents were like,
بالطبع، كان والداي يبدوان هكذا،
"Oh, [it's just a phase.] He'll come back."
أوه، لابد أنها مرحلة قصيرة، وسيعود حتماً"
But life as an artist in New York was not easy,
لكن الحياة كفنان في مدينة نيويورك ليست سهلة
because I was broke,
ولأنني كنتُ مفساً،
no money, no gallery agents, no representation,
لا مال، لا وكالات معارض، لا تمثيل،
so no gallery would show my work.
لذلك لم يكن أي معرض يعرض أعمالي.
So I thought to myself, I need to survive.
لذلك فكرت بنفسي، علي النجاة.
So I started painting on clothes to make a living.
لذلك بدأت بالرسم على الملابس لأؤمن عيشي.
I started painting on shoes.
بدأت بالرسم على الأحذية،
I started customizing things for people.
وبدأت برسم طلبات الناس،
And then soon I realized the power,
ثم بعد ذلك أدركت القوة،
because people were so proud to wear their stories.
لأن الناس كانوا يرتدون قصص الخاصة.
So I started painting on everything.
لذلك بدأت بالرسم على كل شيء.
I painted on guitars,
رسمت على الغيتار،
I started doing murals,
وبدأت برسم الجداريات،
anything I could find my hand on I painted,
كنت أرسم على أي شيء تقع عليه يداي
and everything became my canvas.
وكل شيء بدا كقماشي.
So one day, I was just going on my Instagram feed,
ولذلك ذات يوم، كنت أتصفح الإنستغرام،
and I saw this picture.
عندما رأيت هذه الصورة.
It was Reign. She took a picture standing in front my art,
كانت ريجن. لقد تصورت أمام لوحة لي،
and the moment I saw that photo,
وباللحظة التي رأيت بها هذه الصورة،
something happened in that moment.
حدث شيء بهذه اللحظة.
I could actually see my artwork go into her and come out of her literally,
كان باستطاعتي رؤية لوحتي تعبرها
and that's how I started painting on human bodies.
وهنا بدأت بالرسم على أجسام البشر.
As a child I saw art on the marble floors,
عندما كنت طفلاً رأيت الفن على الأرض الرخامية،
I saw art on walls,
وعلى الحيطان،
but now I see art on people's faces and people's bodies.
لكن الآن أرى الفن على وجوه وأجساد البشر،
I remember my grandmother,
وأتذكر جدتي،
and I realized that most of my creative instincts
وأدركت ان أغلب حدسي الإبداعي
were actually based on my childhood memories
كان أساسه ذكرياتي وأنا طفل
and the art on my grandmother's skin.
والفن على جلد جدتي.
Now I look at all the people I painted, and I think to myself, like,
والآن، أفكر بجميع الأشخاص اللذين رسمت عليهم، وفكرت
what would it look like if we all walked around
كيف سيبدو اذا مشينا كلنا
like gods and goddesses from Yoruba mythology?
مثل الآلهة والآلهات من أساطير اليوربا؟
And boom, that's how The Sacred Art of the Ori was born.
ثم فجأة، هكذا ولدت لوحة "الفن المقدس من أوري"
You see, Ori in Yoruba mythology
وكما ترون، اليوري في الأساطير اليوربيا
means your soul, it means your essence, it means your instincts.
تعني روحك، وجوهرك، وتعني حدسك.
And I realized that only when you tap into your Ori,
ولاحظت انك عندما تضغط على الأوري
then you can actually move mountains.
عندها فقط تستطيع ان تحرك جبال.
So there's something so immediate about painting on human bodies.
لذلك هناك شيء فوري عندما ترسم على الأجسام البشرية.
It's like art in motion.
يبدو الأمر كالفن الذي يتحرك
It's like a 3D experience.
مثل تجربة ثلاثية الأبعاد.
So one day, I was just doing my regular work in Brooklyn,
لذلك يوماً ما، كنتُ أقوم بعملي المعتاد في بروكلين،
and I got an email that said,
عندما تلقيت أيميل،
"Hi, I'm a big fan of your work.
"مرحباً، أنا معجب كبير بعملك،
Would you like to paint for my music video?
هل ترغب بالرسم في أغنيتي المصورة الجديدة؟
Signed, Beyoncé."
التوقيع، بيونسيه"
Like, Beyoncé emailed me.
أجل، أرسلت بيونسيه أيميلاً لي.
I was like, what?
كنت، ماذا ؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I was like, what, how did she even know me?
كنت أفكر من اين عرفتني؟
I thought this can't be true. Of course I thought it was a scam.
اعتقدت انهُ شيء مزيف لابد أنه أيميل خاردع.
The Nigerian in me was like, nah.
والشاب النيجيري في داخلي يقول لا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But incredibly enough, it was real, it was true,
لكن بطريقة غير معقولة كان حقيقياً، كان صحيحاً،
and things happened really fast.
والأشياء حدثت بسرعة كبيرة.
You see, Beyoncé wanted to pay homage to New Orleans,
وكما ترون، أرادت بيونسية أن تحيي نيوأورلنز،
and my art reminded her of her creole origins.
وذكرها فني بأصلها.
So when "Lemonade" dropped, of course,
لذلك عندما صدر ألبوم"ليومونادا"
boom, everything just went from zero to 100 real fast.
بوم، انتقل كل شيء من صفر الى 100 بسرعة كبيرة.
People featured me in magazines,
وصدرت صورتي في المجلات،
interviews.
والمقابلات،
People stopped me in the street.
وأوقفني الناس في الشراع.
People knew my name, like --
عرف الناس اسمي،
And sometimes I had to step back
وكان علي أن أمشي للوراء
and just chill, and, like, take everything in.
واهدء نفسي قليلاً، لأستوعب كل شيء.
You know, as artists, we work so hard all our lives
وكما تعلمون، كفنانين علينا العمل كثيراً طوال حياتنا.
and for this I feel blessed.
ولهذا أشعر بأني مبارك.
However, the attorney in me is still there,
ومع ذلك، مازال المحامي في داخلي موجوداً،
so I use my art to fight for what I believe in.
لذلك استخدمت فني حتى أحارب من أجل ما أؤمن به.
My Yoruba heritage is always there.
وتراث اليوروبا سيبقى هنا.
I'd like to share with you tonight some of my art in motion.
وأرغب في أن أشارككم الليلة بعضاً من فني المتحرك.
Please, welcome with me on stage.
أرجوكم، رحبوا معي على خشبة المسرح،
(Music)
(موسيقا)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now, this is Geli, and this is Reign.
والآن، هذا غيل، وهذه ريجن
These are the first two people I ever painted in my life,
وهذان هما أول شخصان رسمت على اجسامهما في حياتي،
and I spent the past day painting on them.
وأمضيت اليوم السابق بالرسم عليهما،
Tonight, they represent my hopes and my fears.
واليوم، يمثلان أمالي ومخاوفي.
Now, I put my fears on the back.
والآن، وضعت مخاوفي في الخلف.
I put my hopes in front.
وأمالي في المقدمة.
What are my hopes?
ماهي امالي؟
I hope that people know
ارغب بأن يعرف الناس
that Africa is not just one huge, nameless continent
بأن أفريقا ليست مجرد قارة ضخمة مجهولة
that is all the same.
وليست متشابهة.
I also hope that people know
وأرغب بان يعرف الناس
that in Nigeria, we have over 350 ethnic groups and languages,
بأنه في نيجيريا، لدينا أكثر من 350 مجموعة عرقية ولغة،
and I am just one artist from one of them.
وأنا مجرد فنان واحد منهم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I also hope that you know that I hope I will be able to change
وأرغب بأن تعرفوا بأنني أتمنى أن اكون قادراً على تغيير
the way people talk about African art on the continent and here,
الطريقة التي يتحدث بها الناس عن الفن الأفريقي كأنه فن قارة واحدة هنا،
and I hope you know that African art
وأتمنى ان تعرفوا بان الفن الأفريقي
is not just what you buy at Harlem markets in New York
ليس ماتشتريه فقط في متاجر هرلم في نيويرك
and that every piece of art you see has a story,
وأن لكل قطعة فنية تراها هناك قصة،
and every artist has a name.
ولكل فنان اسم.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)